<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ecologies on A. Poupeau Website</title>
    <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Ecologies on A. Poupeau Website</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <atom:link href="https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1st Atlantic Crossing by a Oil Tanker Ship</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/1889.atlanticcrossing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/1889.atlanticcrossing/</guid>
      <description>Oil market becomes global In order to introduce some context, let me talk about The Petroleum Production Company Nobel Brothers or simply Branobel which is a contraction for &amp;ldquo;Nobel Brothers&amp;rdquo; in Russian. The Nobel&amp;rsquo;s Oil company was founded in 1876 in Baku, today&amp;rsquo;s capital of Azerbaïdjan. At some point in history, the Branobel company was producing 50% of all the oil in the world.&#xA;In 1878, Ludvig Nobel, brother of Robert Nobel and of the certainly most well-known Alfred Nobel, ordered the first oil tanker in history called the Zoroaster to a Swedish company.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>1st Patented Gasoline Car</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/1886.car/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/1886.car/</guid>
      <description>The beginning of a revolution The Benz Patent-Motorwagen , built in 1885 by the German Carl Benz, is widely regarded as the world&amp;rsquo;s first practical automobile.&#xA;It was patented in 1886 by Carl Benz, name known today for the company Mercedes-Benz.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2°C limit origin</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/1995.03.degreesorigin/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/1995.03.degreesorigin/</guid>
      <description>Knowing where this limit comes from To put it simply, the 2°C objective comes from a scientific-political coproduction with some major actors like the IPCC and the German Advisory Council on Climate Change (WBGU), an independent scientific advisory body established in the 1992 in the run-up to Rio Earth Summit.&#xA;In 1995, the WBGU proposed a logical and simple approach to determine the threshold that we should never pass. The WBGU claims that the temperature window should not exceed the temperature where biological and human life has been developped on Earth for the past 120000 years.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Air Pollution</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2021.09.airpollution/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2021.09.airpollution/</guid>
      <description>Air pollution contributes to 11.65% of deaths globally The World Health Organization (WHO) published two fact sheets in 2021 that present the latest data:&#xA;WHO – Fact sheet: Ambient (outdoor) air pollution WHO – Fact sheet: Household (indoor) air pollution and health According to estimates, air pollution kills 7 millions people each year and is one of the leading risk factors for death. In low-income countries, it is often very near the top of the list (or is the leading risk factor).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Inconvenient Truth</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2006.05.inconvenient/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2006.05.inconvenient/</guid>
      <description>A documentary film to educate people about global warming Al Gore was back then the Vice President of the United States when he wrote the film An Inconvenient Truth (see trailer) . Thanks to his work he obtained a Nobel Peace Prize in 2007 for drawing the world&amp;rsquo;s attention to the dangers of global warming which is the centerpiece in the film. I can not stress enough how much I recommend you to watch it.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Approching a State Shift in Earth Biosphere</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/books/approachingastateshiftinearthbiosphere/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/books/approachingastateshiftinearthbiosphere/</guid>
      <description>Review evidence that the Global Ecosystem is approaching a planetary-scale critical transition as a result of human influence</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Are we on the brink of a pronunced Global Warming</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/books/areweonthebrinkofapronuncedglobalwarming/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/books/areweonthebrinkofapronuncedglobalwarming/</guid>
      <description>An old Science report that predicted the temperature rise levels for years to come back in 1975. Its predictions are correct and it further explores what may go wrong in the case of a pronunced global warming.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Be Worried. Be Very Worried.</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/books/beworriedbeveryworried/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/books/beworriedbeveryworried/</guid>
      <description>Earth at the Tipping Point: Global Warming Heats Up</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Berlin Conference COP1</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/1995.04.cop1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/1995.04.cop1/</guid>
      <description>The first Conference Of Parties In 1995, the first COP took place in Berlin where 120 governments were represented. Even though the first IPCC report was released in 1990 and announced a possible 3°C global warming in 2050 compared to the pre-industrial era, the scientific alarm is not really taken seriously. The conference did not end with concrete measures.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Blast, Independent media</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/actions/blast/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/actions/blast/</guid>
      <description>Click here and watch a video that gathers some examples of actions to take.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Brundtland Report</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/1987.brundtland/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/1987.brundtland/</guid>
      <description>A famous report on Sustainable Development The Bruntland Report also known for its title Our Common Future, is an ordered report by the United Nations on the subject of Sustainable Development.&#xA;&#34;It was an urgent call by the General Assembly of the United Nations to propose long-term environmental strategies for achieving sustainable development by the year 2000 and beyond. [...] The Earth is one but the world is not. [...] A sustainable society is one that meets the need of the present without compromising the ability of future generations to meet their own needs.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Carbon Bombs</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2022.05.carbonbombs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2022.05.carbonbombs/</guid>
      <description>425 Carbon Bombs worldwide &#34;We have mapped the biggest fossil fuel projects worldwide, 425 carbon bombs, with a CO2 emissions potential exceeding 1 Gigaton in each project. The potential emissions from these projects exceed the 1.5 °C carbon budget by a factor of two. We showed that there is a high concentration of these projects in countries that have so far received little attention by those looking at the supply side of climate change mitigation: China, Middle Eastern countries and Russia.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Climate Fresk</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/actions/climatefresk/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/actions/climatefresk/</guid>
      <description>Like lots of people and I, you can become a facilitator to animate workshops on climate change!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Climate Refugees Estimations</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2020.09.refugees/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2020.09.refugees/</guid>
      <description>Between 200 millions and 1.2 billion climate refugees by 2050 The Institute of Economics and Peace produces reports each year on different themes related to economics and peace. The ones we are particularly interested in are the Ecological Threat Reports - one was published in 2020 and another in 2021.&#xA;&#34;6.4 billion people live in countries which are exposed to medium to high ecological threats. [...] An estimated 1.2 billion people are at risk of displacement by 2050.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Climate Spiral</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2022.03.climatespiral/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2022.03.climatespiral/</guid>
      <description>NASA Visualization of Global Temperature Evolution This visualization shows monthly global temperature anomalies (changes from an average) between the years 1880 and 2021. Whites and blues indicate cooler temperatures, while oranges and reds show warmer temperatures. As you can see, global temperatures have warmed from mainly human activities as time has progressed.&#xA;These temperatures are based on data from NASA&amp;rsquo;s Goddard Institute for Space Studies (GISS). Anomalies are defined relative to a base period of 1951 to 1980.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Copenhagen Summit COP15</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2009.copenhagen/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2009.copenhagen/</guid>
      <description>From Hopenhagen to Flopenhagen There was hope before this conference. The event was even called Hopenhagen but it unfortunately turned into Flopenhagen. Indeed with the election of Barack Obama at the end of 2009, there was hope for the United States to reintegrate the Kyoto Protocol but it was not the case.&#xA;China became the first emitter of CO2 emissions in the world (China exceeded USA in 2004 to be precise) but is still defending itself by hammering on the historical responsability due to past emissions argument.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Creation of the United Nations</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/1945.un/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/1945.un/</guid>
      <description>Maintaining peace and security The United Nations was created in 1945. This international organization was established right after World War II with the aim of preventing future wars however its role has extended to environmental concerns.&#xA;The United Nations has played a central role in the international environmental scene by:&#xA;Encouraging the creation of the World Meteorological Organization in 1950&#xA;Organizing the Stockholm Conference , the first international environmental conference in 1972 which resulted in the creation of the United Nations Environmental Programme (UNEP).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deux Degrés</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/books/deuxdegres/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/books/deuxdegres/</guid>
      <description>Another book on the climate change subject: it does not provide more information if you are already informed. It nonetheless offers a different point of view about it.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Devant l&#39;Effondrement</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/books/devantleffondrement/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/books/devantleffondrement/</guid>
      <description>A hard-to-read book because of the conclusion it suggests : a collapse of our society probably in 2020 and certain before 2030.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discovery of the Plastic Ocean</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/1997.plasticocean/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/1997.plasticocean/</guid>
      <description>Discovery of the 7th continent In 1997, Captain Charles Moore discovered the Great Pacific Garbage Patch (GPGP)&amp;ndash; a whirlpool of plastic debris in the Pacific Ocean. This is the biggest accumulation of plastic in a ocean gyre. It extends over 3 millions km2 or 6 times the area of France.&#xA;Plastic we create unfortunately ends up in the ocean. According to a WWF report , between 86-150 million metric tonnes (MMT) of plastic have accumulated in the oceans in 2022, at a continuously increasing rate: in 2010, 4.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Don&#39;t even think about it</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/books/donteventhinkaboutit/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/books/donteventhinkaboutit/</guid>
      <description>A psychological approach to the question : why don&amp;rsquo;t we care about climate change ?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dormez tranquilles jusqu&#39;en 2100</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/books/dormeztranquillesjusquen2100/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/books/dormeztranquillesjusquen2100/</guid>
      <description>A book har to read in my opinion as it goes in all directions, left and right, with a confusing structure. I would better recommend Jean-Marc Jancovici&amp;rsquo;s conferences (available on Youtube for example): he is clearer orally.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dubai COP28</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2023.12.cop28/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2023.12.cop28/</guid>
      <description>A Historic Deal The 28th Conference of Parties was a scandal from the start for some people:&#xA;it was organized in Dubaï United Arab Emirates (UAE), the 7th oil productor in the world.&#xA;the president chosen for the 28th COP is the Sultan Al-Jaber; he is the Industry Minister of the UAE and the CEO of the Abu Dhabi National Oil Company (ADNOC). However, this company is aiming for a oil production capacity boost to 5 million b/d by 2030 from about 4 million b/d in 2022 (see also the International Trade Administration UAE Comercial Guide published in November 25, 2023) which is a 25% oil production increase even though the 28th UN Climate Change Conference mentions: World agrees to transition away from fossil fuels and reduce global emissions by 43% by 2030 .</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Earth Day</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2022.04.earthday/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2022.04.earthday/</guid>
      <description>The UN Secretary-General says that governments are lying to us &#34;We are on a pathway to global warming of more than double the 1.5-degree limit agreed in Paris. Some government and business leaders are saying one thing – but doing another. Simply put, they are lying. And the results will be catastrophic. This is a climate emergency. [...] Climate activists are sometimes depicted as dangerous radicals. But the truly dangerous radicals are the countries that are increasing the production of fossil fuels.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Earthmasters</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/books/earthmasters/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/books/earthmasters/</guid>
      <description>Deconstruction of the myth of geo-engineering solutions and explains how some people want to play god with the climate.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Existential Threat to Humanity</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2018.05.unthreat/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2018.05.unthreat/</guid>
      <description>Climate change is an existencial threat to humanity The 15 May 2018, UN Secretary-General António Guterres delivered a message at the Austrian World Summit emphasizing that climate change is an existencial threat to humanity.&#xA;&#34;If we fail to meet the challenge [of climate change], all our other challenges will just become greater and threaten to swallow us. Climate change is, quite simply, an existential threat for most life on the planet - including, and especially, the life of humankind.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First Earth Day</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/1970.firstearthday/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/1970.firstearthday/</guid>
      <description>Emergence of environmental consciousness April 22nd 1970, the first Earth Day is celebrated; the environmental movement attains strong influence, spreads concern about global degradation. An estimated 20 million people nationwide attended the inaugural events at tens of thousands of sites including elementary and secondary schools, universities, and community sites across the United States.&#xA;In 1970, the U.S. National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration , the world&amp;rsquo;s leading funder of climate research, is created.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>French Environment Minister quits</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2018.08.hulot/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2018.08.hulot/</guid>
      <description>He says: &amp;ldquo;I do not want to lie anymore&amp;rdquo; Nicolas Hulot was the Environment Minister from May 2017 to Sept. 2018. Quiting was for him a way to protest. In his opinion, to prolong his mission would have been a synonym of resignation. Indeed, to prolong was like giving the illusion to people that we are going in the right direction.&#xA;&#34;We think that ecology means just a subtle change ; no it is a real software change, a paradigm change.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global Decline in Insects</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2017.insects/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2017.insects/</guid>
      <description>Average decline of 76% in 27 years. &#34;Loss of insect diversity and abundance is expected to provoke cascading effects on food webs and to jeopardize ecosystem services. [...] Our analysis estimates a seasonal decline of 76%, and mid-summer decline of 82% in flying insect biomass over the 27 years of study. [...] 80% of wild plants are estimated to depend on insects for pollination, while 60% of birds rely on insects as a food source.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global Decline in Vertebrates</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2020.01.vertebrates/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2020.01.vertebrates/</guid>
      <description>Average decline of 68% in 46 years &#34;The global Living Planet Index (LPI) continues to decline. It shows an average 68% decrease in population sizes of mammals, birds, amphibians, reptiles and fish between 1970 and 2016. A 94% decline in the LPI for the tropical subregions of the Americas is the largest fall observed in any part of the world.&#34;&#xA;—Marco Lambertini Director General WWF International, WWF Living Planet Report 2020, first paragraph of the executive summary, 2020 </description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global Peak Oil</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2023.10.peakglobaloil/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2023.10.peakglobaloil/</guid>
      <description>The Decline of Black Gold around 2030 We have seen that according to the World Energy Outlook 2018 report at page 45: &amp;ldquo;Global conventional crude oil production peaked in 2008 at 69.5 million barrils per day (mb/d) and has since fallen by around 2.5 mb/d.&amp;rdquo;. Nonetheless, we have not seen any impacts or changes since 2008; no crisis occured like in 1973. Why ? This can be explained because of the production of unconventional oil which have counterbalanced the fall of conventional crude oil production since then.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gouverner le Climat</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/books/gouvernerleclimat/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/books/gouvernerleclimat/</guid>
      <description>This is a great book that goes through the history of all the international conferences about climate change and shows how and why things have not evolved.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Greenpeace</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/actions/greenpeace/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/actions/greenpeace/</guid>
      <description>Greenpeace is a network of independent organisations, which uses peaceful, creative confrontation to expose global environmental problems, and develop solutions for a green and peaceful future.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>IEA Roadmap</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2021.06.iearoadmap/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2021.06.iearoadmap/</guid>
      <description>Pathway to critical goal of net-zero emissions by 2050 &#34;[...] the Roadmap sets out more than 400 milestones to guide the global journey to net zero by 2050. These include, from today, no investment in new fossil fuel supply projects, and no further final investment decisions for new unabated coal plants. By 2035, there are no sales of new internal combustion engine passenger cars, and by 2040, the global electricity sector has already reached net-zero emissions.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/1988.ipcc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/1988.ipcc/</guid>
      <description>Ensuring access to scientific knowledge on climate change The Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) is an organization that provides objective and comprehensive scientific information on anthropogenic climate change, including the natural, political, and economic impacts and risks, and possible response options. It does not conduct original research nor monitor climate change, but rather undertakes a periodic, systematic review of all relevant published literature. Thousands of scientists and other experts volunteer to review the data and compile key findings into &amp;ldquo;Assessment Reports&amp;rdquo; for policymakers and the general public.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>International Energy Agency</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/1974.iea/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/1974.iea/</guid>
      <description>Essential reports on Energy The International Energy Agency (IEA) created in 1974 is well-known for its annual high quality reports on the question of energy called World Energy Outlook . The IEA provides an expertise to nations to help them formulate their energy policies and helps to frame the energy debate on a global scale.&#xA;Even though the World Energy Outlook are unmissable reports, I can only encourage you to take a look at different sources such as:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Invention of Plastic</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/1907.plastic/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/1907.plastic/</guid>
      <description>The most inappropriate material for its use 1907 is the year of birth of industrial plastic with the invention of bakelite. Other discoveries subsequently opened the door to more intensive use.&#xA;We, humans, have chosen to create a material that is highly durable for short-life or even single uses. Indeed, for example it takes around 450 years for a plastic bottle to be decomposed into microplastics that are even more dangerous than macroplastic because it enters the food chain.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>IPCC</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/actions/ipcc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/actions/ipcc/</guid>
      <description>Hundreds of experts in different fields volunteer their time and expertise to produce IPCC reports. Thousands more contribute to the review process and to the literature and other knowledge that are assessed in IPCC reports. These scientists are not paid by the IPCC.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>IPCC Report on 1.5°C Global Warming</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2018.10.special/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2018.10.special/</guid>
      <description>Special report There are only 14 IPCC special reports currently. They are intended to specify some elements that could not have been made in other reports. IPCC considered it useful to publish a special report on the theme of Global Warming 1.5°C because they thought it could help understand that this threshold is already critical and to be avoided: Link to the special report .&#xA;Keeping the global temperature rise below 1.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>IPCC reports</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/books/ipcc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/books/ipcc/</guid>
      <description>The most important and reliable scientific source about climate change.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Keeling Curve</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/1958.keelingcurve/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/1958.keelingcurve/</guid>
      <description>Proof of the accumulation of CO2 in the atmosphere The curve is named after the scientist Charles David Keeling who started the continuous CO2 monitoring program and supervised it from 1958 until his death in 2005.&#xA;I recommend to take a look at The Keeling Curve site to explore interactively the different time ranges and see that the concentration of CO2 has exploded since the industrial revolution in 1850. For those who prefer to learn through videos, here is a great official one minute video from the Scripps Oceanography Institute: The Keeling Curve Hits 415 PPM video I strongly want to hammer on the fact that the current CO2 concentration has nothing to do with a natural variability as you can see on the following graph.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Keeling Report</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/1963.keelingreport/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/1963.keelingreport/</guid>
      <description>Connecting the dots : CO2 rise implies global temperature rise Keeling&amp;rsquo;s curve was rising year by year through the 1960s. In 1963, Keeling and a few other experts met at a conference sponsored by the private Conservation Foundation and issued a report suggesting that the doubling of CO2 projected for the next century could raise the world&amp;rsquo;s temperature by 3.8 Fahrenheit or 2.1°C.&#xA;&#34;It is estimated that a doubling of the carbon dioxide content of the atmosphere would produce an average atmospheric temperature rise of 3.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kyoto Protocol</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/1997.12.kyoto/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/1997.12.kyoto/</guid>
      <description>The first real but narrow objectives are set The third COP took place in Kyoto in Japan in 1997 and concluded with the elaboration of the Kyoto Protocol. The Protocol was opened for signatures in 1998 and came into effect in 2005 after 175 governments signed it - but not the United States which represented 36% of global emission in 1990. The Protocol specifies the 1992 Framework Convention by assigning real emission reduction objectives for each signatory nation to reach before 2012 but without sanction mechanisms.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>L&#39;Age des Low Tech</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/books/agedeslowtech/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/books/agedeslowtech/</guid>
      <description>A focus on the ressource part of the systemic concern in the Anthropocene in particular about metals and rare ressources used in our High Technologies.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>L&#39;Humanité en péril</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/books/humaniteenperilvironsdebord/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/books/humaniteenperilvironsdebord/</guid>
      <description>Fred Vargas is mostly well-known for her crime novels however she wrote a transparent and really easy to read (even for neophytes) book about the systemic problems due to Anthropocene. The book is quite naive and its approach is sometimes confusing but it at least informs people about climate change, biodiversity destruction, energy and more.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Merchants of Doubt</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/books/merchantsofdoubt/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/books/merchantsofdoubt/</guid>
      <description>How a Handful of Scientists Obscured the Truth on Issues from Tobacco Smoke to Global Warming.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Momentum Institute</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/actions/momentum/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/actions/momentum/</guid>
      <description>The main purpose of this association is to assemble contributors around the issues of transition, degrowth and resilience.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Montreal COP11 / MOP1</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2005.mop1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2005.mop1/</guid>
      <description>The first Meeting Of Parties (MOP) The 2005 United Nations Climate Change Conference took place between November 28 and December 9, 2005, in Montreal, Quebec, Canada. The conference included the COP11, and was the first Meeting of the Parties (MOP1) to the Kyoto Protocol since their initial meeting in Kyoto in 1997.&#xA;The conference was one of the largest intergovernmental conferences on climate change ever. The event marked the entry into force of the Kyoto Protocol on 16 February 2005.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More Plastic than Fish</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2016.01.plasticfish/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2016.01.plasticfish/</guid>
      <description>An unconceivable and monumentally absurd idea A report published in January 19, 2016 estimated that there will be more plastic than fish by weight by 2050. The UN President of the 73rd Session reacted in June 2019 :&#xA;&#34;If we do nothing, by 2050, our world’s oceans will have more plastic in them than fish (by weight). I am going to repeat this, because it is an idea that appears monumentally absurd, but according to a report by the World Economic Forum and Ellen MacArthur Foundation, this is exactly the future we are headed toward: There will be more plastic than fish in the ocean in just over 30 years.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Only One Earth</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/1972.01.onlyoneearth/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/1972.01.onlyoneearth/</guid>
      <description>A classic in ecological literature The book was originally an ordered report for the Stockholm conference that occurred the year of its publication. The report already mentions the main concerns we are facing now : malnutrition, ocean acidification and more. Surprisingly, the 2°C global warming threshold already appears in this old report.&#xA;&#34;The equilibrium between incoming and outgoing radiation, the forces that preserve the global temperature seem so delicate, so precise, that a slight change in the energy equilibrium could disturb everything.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Or Noir</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/books/ornoir/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/books/ornoir/</guid>
      <description>An essay about oil history, from its discovery to its importance in today&amp;rsquo;s civilization in all domains: industrial of course but also military, political and economical.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Paris Agreement COP21</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2015.12.parisagreement/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2015.12.parisagreement/</guid>
      <description>Lots of joy and promises Paris Agreement aims to reach zero net CO2 emissions by 2050: is it even possible ? Well let us be realistic for 5 seconds, if we consider a net zero emission by 2100 then (see graph from Our World in Data) :&#xA;In the Copenhagen Conference back in 2009, an analysis was made that indicates that in order not to reach 2°C we needed to have a 3% reduction of global emission of greenhouse gazes per year.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Peak of Conventional Crude Oil</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2008.01.peakcrudeoil/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2008.01.peakcrudeoil/</guid>
      <description>The End of Black Gold ? According to the World Energy Outlook 2010 report at page 48, conventional crude oil production peaked in 2006, with an all-time maximum of 70 million barrels per day (mb/d). 2006 was refined to 2008 in the World Energy Outlook 2018 report at page 45: &amp;ldquo;Global conventional crude oil production peaked in 2008 at 69.5 mb/d and has since fallen by around 2.5 mb/d.&amp;rdquo;&#xA;&#34;All the easy oil and gas in the world has pretty much been found.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Penser la décroissance</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/books/penserladecroissance/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/books/penserladecroissance/</guid>
      <description>A book written by different specialists where each has its own chapter. There are two books that follow after this one.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Planet Boundaries</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2023.09.planetboundaries/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2023.09.planetboundaries/</guid>
      <description>9 boundaries accessed, 6 crossed The planetary boundaries concept appeared in 2009. It presents a set of nine planetary boundaries within which humanity can continue to develop and thrive for generations to come. In September 2023, a team of scientists quantified, for the first time, all nine processes that regulate the stability and resilience of the Earth system. For more information, visit the website stockholmesresilience.org or read the 2023 scientific paper Earth beyond six of nine planetary boundaries .</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Planetary Boundaries</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/books/planetaryboundaries/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/books/planetaryboundaries/</guid>
      <description>Earth beyond six of nine planetary boundaries</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reduce your carbon footprint</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/actions/carbonfootprint/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/actions/carbonfootprint/</guid>
      <description>Currently the french mean is around 10t CO2 per year but let&amp;rsquo;s reach 2t CO2 per year !</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rio de Janeiro Earth Summit</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/1992.earthsummit/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/1992.earthsummit/</guid>
      <description>The beginning of the Climate Regime The United Nations Conference on Environment and Development (UNCED), also called the Earth Summit, is really important: 172 governments are represented, 117 heads of state are present and around 2400 NGO leaders are there too.&#xA;The conference addressed global issues such as fossil fuels, climate change, public transportation and more. At the end of the event various conventions and policies are produced like the Agenda 21 .</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shift your job</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/actions/shifter/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/actions/shifter/</guid>
      <description>A way to see what job could have an direct or indirect impact on the revolution and that fits you.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stern Review</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2006.11.stern/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2006.11.stern/</guid>
      <description>The Economics of Climate Change Nicholas Stern, former vice-president of the World Bank Group, is a British doctor in economy and a member of various institutions such as the University of Oxford. In October 2006, he published a 662 pages report called the Stern Review: The Economics of Climate Change to the attention of the Prime Minister and the Chancellor of the Exchequer of the United Kingdom.&#xA;&#34;There is still time to avoid the worst impacts of climate change, if we take strong action now.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stockholm Conference</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/1972.06.stockholmconf/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/1972.06.stockholmconf/</guid>
      <description>Exposing environmental issues on the international scene The Stockholm Conference is the first world conference on the environment. The UN was dedicated to make the environment a major issue.&#xA;One of the major results of the Stockholm conference was the creation of the United Nations Environmental Programme (UNEP) which is responsible for coordinating responses to environmental issues within the United Nations system.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Coal Question</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/1865.coal/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/1865.coal/</guid>
      <description>An economist ahead of its time &amp;ldquo;Are we wise in allowing the commerce of this country to rise beyond the point at which we can long maintain it?&amp;rdquo; asked rhetorically the british economist Stanley Jevons in 1865 in his book The Coal Question: An Inquiry Concerning the Progress of the Nation, and the Probable Exhaustion of Our Coal Mines . Mr Jevons was a visionnary, indeed he was already conscious of three important points:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Discovery of Global Warming</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/books/discoveryglobalwarming/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/books/discoveryglobalwarming/</guid>
      <description>History about how Global Warming was discovered.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Eleventh Hour</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2007.eleventhhour/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2007.eleventhhour/</guid>
      <description>A documentary film on the state of the Natural Environment With contributions from over 50 politicians, scientists, and environmental activists, including former Soviet leader Mikhail Gorbachev, physicist Stephen Hawking, Nobel Prize winner Wangari Maathai, journalist Armand Betscher, and Paul Hawken, the film documents the serious problems facing the planet&amp;rsquo;s life systems. Global warming, deforestation, mass species extinction, and depletion of the oceans&amp;rsquo; habitats are all addressed. The film&amp;rsquo;s premise is that the future of humanity is in jeopardy.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Great Acceleration</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2015.03.greatacc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2015.03.greatacc/</guid>
      <description>Exponentials everywhere A report named Great Acceleration was originally published in 2004 to show socio-economic and Earth System trends from 1750 to 2000. In a 2015 report named The Trajectory of the Anthropocene: The Great Acceleration , graphs were updated to 2010.&#xA;Socio-Economic Trends Earth System Trends &#34;Will the next 50 years bring the Great Decoupling or the Great Collapse? The latest 10 years of the Great Acceleration graphs show signs of both but cannot distinguish between these scenarios, or other possibilities.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Limits to Growth</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/books/thelimitstogrowth/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/books/thelimitstogrowth/</guid>
      <description>A classic and a must-read. New editions have been published in 1992, 2004 and 2012.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Limits To Growth</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/1972.03.ltg/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/1972.03.ltg/</guid>
      <description>Prediction of a Collapse of our Societies This unmissable book - it really is a must-read - is a report of a two year study by the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT) from 1970 to 1972. The project team used system dynamics theory and computer modeling to analyze, via a computer model named World3 , the long-term causes and consequences of growth in the world&amp;rsquo;s population and material economy. Their conclusions are unpleasant but must be read carefully:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Psychology of Climate Change Communication</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/books/communication/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/books/communication/</guid>
      <description>A great psychological guide for anybody interested in enhancing its communication skills about climate change and more.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Unhabitable Earth</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/books/unhabitableearth/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/books/unhabitableearth/</guid>
      <description>The book explores various possibilities for Earth&amp;rsquo;s future across a spectrum of predicted future temperature ranges. Wallace-Wells&amp;rsquo; argues that even with active intervention, the effects of climate change will have catastrophic impacts across multiple spheres.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>This Changes Everything</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/books/thischangeseverything/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/books/thischangeseverything/</guid>
      <description>This is a must-read in order to understand the systemic causes and consequences in the Anthropocene.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trajectories of the Earth System</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/books/trajectoriesearthsystem/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/books/trajectoriesearthsystem/</guid>
      <description>We explore the risk that self-reinforcing feedbacks could push the Earth System toward a planetary threshold that, if crossed, could prevent stabilization of the climate at intermediate temperature rises and cause continued warming on a “Hothouse Earth” pathway even as human emissions are reduced.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>United Nations 1st Warning</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/1969.unfirstwarning/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/1969.unfirstwarning/</guid>
      <description>His thoughts about the systemic concern &#34;I do not wish to seem overdramatic, but I can only conclude from the information that is available to me as Secretary-General, that the Members of the United Nations have perhaps ten years left in which to subordinate their ancient quarrels and launch a global partnership to curb the arms race, to improve the human environment, to defuse the population explosion, and to supply the required momentum to development efforts.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Warmest Years</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2024.01.warmestyears/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2024.01.warmestyears/</guid>
      <description>2023 is the warmest year since global records 2023 is officially the warmest year ever recorded. The National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA) makes it clear in its article Climate Change: Global Temperature published on January 18, 2024. The important highlights are the following: 2023 was the warmest year since global records began in 1850 by a wide margin and worst than that, the 10 warmest years in the historical record have all occurred in the past decade (2014-2023).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What to do ?</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/now/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/now/</guid>
      <description>Study, Share and Act You can be a thinker, a maker, an instigator, an organiser or a facilitator (Arthur Keller - 2022).&#xA;The important thing it to stop denying. If we deeply understand we will act accordingly. Even though Naomi Klein is focused on climate change, this applies for the systemic concern:&#xA;A great many of us engage in this kind of climate change denial. We look for a split second and then we look away.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why Climat Change does not Scare Us Yet ?</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/books/whyclimatechangedoesnotscareusyet/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/books/whyclimatechangedoesnotscareusyet/</guid>
      <description>A psychological approach to answer the question : Why Climate Change does not scare us yet ?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>World Bank Report</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2012.wbreport/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/2012.wbreport/</guid>
      <description>Turn Down the Heat The report is called Turn Down the Heat: Why a 4°C Warmer World Must Be Avoided (available in English, French and Spanish). The funny fact is that it was written by an unexpected organization which we may consider as uninterested by the systemic crisis or even in part responsible of it: the World Bank. However, even their leaders realized that the crisis may be a problem for them.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>World Meteorological Organization</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/1950.wmo/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/timeline/1950.wmo/</guid>
      <description>Promoting a shared vision The World Meteorological Organization (WMO) is an institution created in 1950 that played a huge role in the emergence of the human-caused greenhouse effect question on the international scene. The WMO has three main objectives :&#xA;Harmonize norms and national pratices through international technical and scientific cooperation.&#xA;Build or reinforce the states&amp;rsquo; capacities to conduct their own research and to maintain a dedicated technological infrastructure.&#xA;Mobilize the international community around global concerns by promoting a shared vision.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>World Wide Fund for Nature</title>
      <link>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/actions/wwf/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexandrepoupeau.com/ecology/actions/wwf/</guid>
      <description>As the world’s leading conservation organization, WWF works in nearly 100 countries to tackle the most pressing issues at the intersection of nature, people, and climate.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
